what's up my piano friends today i'm
going to teach you the top four mistakes
beginners always make on piano that
really hurts their progress especially
for adult learners and people trying to
teach themselves off of youtube and some
of these are so easy to fix in just a
few minutes if you know what your
problem is and how to solve it and
you're going to want to stick around
because each mistake gets more and more
important up until the final mistake
which is absolutely critical for your
success if you ever want to be good at
piano let's start off with mistake
number one which believe it or not is
learning to read sheet music and i know
what you're thinking you're thinking
zack piano teachers always say that it's
super important to learn how to read
sheet music but that's because they're
all teaching classical style music and
yes if you want to learn how to play
classical music you are going to have to
read notes but if your goal is just to
learn your favorite songs from the radio
you know pop blues jazz rock and roll
oldies these songs are much easier to
learn using a simple google search and a
cheat sheet that's gonna allow even a
complete beginner to learn songs in a
few minutes or less and this is going to
save you absolute boatloads of time and
let me prove it to you by the way if
you've ever been to one of those dueling
piano bars where people are just
requesting all those random songs and
they can just magically play all of them
with no sheet music this is the method
they're using all right so check this
out let's go to this random song
generator and let's just hit random
music
and let's take the first one blank space
by taylor swift i actually really really
like this song so all we gotta do is hop
over to google and type in blank space
chords all right and we have to click on
the first one that pops up and if we
scroll down boom we have the chords for
the entire song so as you can see we
have d
then we have b m which stands for b
minor and then g and then a and just
like almost every pop song out there
it's just going to repeat the same four
chords over and over right we have d b
minor g a and if we keep scrolling down
we have d b minor g a and these four
chords just repeat over and over so now
the easy way to find these chords on
piano is all we have to do is bring up
the ultimate chords cheat sheet and i'll
tell you where to get this cheat sheet
in a bit we just find our chords so we
just find d which is right here then we
find b minor which is right down here
and then we have to find g which is
right up here and then we have to find a
which is right here and boom we have our
four chords to the song and so if we put
these four chords by the piano all we
have to do is copy these shapes all
right so our first shape is d major
which looks like this
our next one is b minor looks like this
i'm just copying the shapes from the
cheat sheet and then g major which looks
like this
and then finally a major which looks
and you practice those for a bit and you
can already play this song
nice to meet you where you been knocking
show you incredible things magic madness
heaven sin saw you there and i thought
oh my god look at that face you look
like my next mistake love's a game do
you wanna play
and already we got the outline to the
song and now it feels a little bit
sparse so to spice it up a bit let's
play each chord eight times and this is
a simple what's called money pattern and
we'll talk more about money patterns
later so we play each chord eight times
now we have d major two three four five
six seven eight b minor two three four
five six seven eight g major two three
four five six seven eight a major two
three four five six seven eight now it's
gonna sound a lot cooler so let's
continue on with the second part of the
verse
[Music]
you like a magazine ain't it funny
rumors fly and i know you heard about me
so hey let's be friends i'm dying to see
how this one ends grab your passport and
my hand
yeah
and boom you can already play blank
space no sheet music necessary how much
easier is that than memorizing note by
note sheet music right and you can do
this for any song if you like the idea
of learning songs this way without sheet
music hit that like button and of course
there are a few other things involved
you know like adding the left hand added
some more you know complicated money
patterns so it can sound more like this
[Music]
and i know if you're a beginner that
probably looked really hard but trust me
it's actually pretty simple to learn
it's just a lot of repeated patterns but
that's a little bit outside the scope of
this video if you're really interested
in learning that system and you want to
learn a ton of songs from the radio i'll
put a link here and in the description
for the top three chord progressions for
beginners video that goes much more in
depth on this process but first we have
to talk about mistake number two and
this is a very important one and that
involves the sloppy choppy playing that
you hear from so many beginners and the
cause of this is actually probably not
what you think so let me ask you a
question right now when you learn
something on piano right and you have a
tricky section is your solution to just
repeat it over and over and just bang
your head against the wall until it
works
and if so you're making it really hard
on yourself okay because we can work
smarter not harder and use other
practice strategies that will solve this
ten times faster so let's take an
example right let's say you're trying to
learn the song apologize by one republic
it sounds like this
but for most beginners out there it
sounds more something like this
right it's very choppy and sloppy and
even though they're playing all the
right notes it doesn't have that smooth
confident feeling to it and so at this
point most beginners just repeat it over
and over for weeks and weeks and weeks
until it finally sounds okay but that's
not really how it works instead we want
to drill in this pattern using the four
rhythms technique okay and here's how it
works so let's just take the first four
notes of the pattern
all we're gonna do is we're gonna repeat
these four notes four times using four
different rhythms okay so step one we're
gonna play these same four notes
but we're gonna use rhythm number one
which is long short long short it's
gonna sound like this
long
short long
short and you're going to repeat that
four times then you're gonna do rhythm
number two which sounds like this
short long
and you're gonna do that four times and
then you move on to rhythm number three
which sounds like this
long
short short short long
short short short you're gonna repeat
that four times and then you're gonna
move on to the final rhythm which sounds
like this
short short short long
and you're gonna repeat that four times
and finally when you go back to playing
it like normal trust me it's going to
magically kind of smooth it out and
it'll sound more like this
and beginners always tell me they're
like zach after using the rhythms
technique it makes it feel like it's in
my fingers and i'm absolutely begging
you to try this because the before and
after just feels so much better in your
hands and this is just the tip of the
iceberg when it comes to practice
strategy by the way if you want the
cheat sheet for these four rhythms plus
the ultimate chords cheat sheet we used
earlier both of those are on the bonuses
page just click the link put in your
name and email hit submit and you can
download both of those cheat sheets here
[Music]
all right on to mistake number three and
this is an important one and that's not
using the over under technique and trust
me if you're not doing this you're going
to be absolutely kicking yourself for
not fixing it sooner because it's so
easy to fix so a lot of beginner players
have what i like to call weak pinky
syndrome where their first four fingers
sound nice and strong and confident but
their pinky feels weak and feeble and do
you ever feel like this when you play
now what most people do is they think
they have to quote unquote strengthen
their pinky by doing these you know
pinky exercises right but it's actually
not a strength issue and in fact there
are no muscles in your pinky it's only
tendons the muscles are actually in your
wrist so you don't solve weak pinky
syndrome by strengthening your pinky you
solve it by fixing your technique let me
show you so if you play piano with
what's called a straight wrist meaning
you have your hands on the keys and your
wrist goes straight back and you keep
your wrist in this position your first
four fingers can solve smooth and
confident
but the problem is your pinky if you
curve it and have it nice and strong and
curved it's not going to be able to play
the note so what beginners do is they
compensate by flattening out their pinky
right so it's easier to reach the note
and they have this very weak pinky sound
but it's a very easy fix all you have to
do is whenever you're playing toward
your pinky on the piano you take your
wrist and you rotate it down and out
okay and now look how curved our pinky
is when our wrist is over here and it
can play nice and strong so now instead
of
weak pinky that barely reaches the keys
we have a
a nice strong peaky because we're
rotating our wrist down and out and this
technique is called the over under
technique or the over under wrist motion
and if you practice this technique for a
few days you can magically have a strong
pinky whenever you play okay and it
kills me because so many beginners out
there spend years trying to quote
unquote strengthen their pinky with
these you know exercises but it's like
no let's work smarter not harder and
just fix your technique and this over
under technique is actually just one of
many motions right many small shifts in
your wrist and your hand that are
absolutely essential if you ever want to
play smooth and confident on the keys
what's really dangerous is as a beginner
the longer you don't use correct
technique like the over under technique
and like some other ones the longer
you're going to drill in bad habits that
can be an absolute nightmare to correct
in the future so if you're interested in
really taking care of your technique
once and for all and the four exercises
that really shore up all of these issues
i have another video called the top four
exercises for piano beginners i'll put
the link to that up here and in the
description which brings me to the final
mistake which is absolutely critical if
you ever want to be a good piano player
before that if you like this style of
teaching where i really cut the fat on
what's actually important to get you up
and running on piano hit that subscribe
button and hit that notification bell
i'd really hate for you to miss out on a
future video that could really change
the whole trajectory of your piano
learning all right on to mistake number
four and this one's important which is
not having a plan of attack on piano and
a ton of beginners out there they sit
down at the piano and they just randomly
kind of waffle around you know instead
of having a laser focused day by day
week by week month by month plan of
attack a workout plan right that's been
proven by hundreds of students to work
time and time again so here's an example
of a plan of attack from mastering your
technique and as you can see we have
week one all the way down through week
12 and for each week we have four
exercises we're learning and each week
we change the key we're learning in
which means we're practicing all four of
these exercises
over different notes on the piano and
once you get done with all 12 weeks
you'll have drilled in correct technique
for every single possible combination of
notes on piano and so what you do is you
sit down in week one you practice
exercise one and once you're done
practicing it you put a little tally
mark in the box
and then you do the same thing for
exercise two you practice it on day one
you put another tally mark in the box
and same for exercise three and exercise
four and then boom this takes about 10
to 15 minutes and you're done for day
one then you'd sit back down at your
piano for day two you do exercise one in
the key of c right and then you put your
little tally mark and then exercise two
and then three and then four and boom
you're done with day two and you would
keep doing this until you have five
tally marks in the box and once you have
five tally marks in the box you can
actually cross that box off the list and
you're done with it and you do the same
thing with exercises two three and four
for week one and then you continue the
same thing for week two where the key
and the notes get gradually harder and
harder and you'd continue all the way up
to week 12 and once you have all these
boxes crossed off boom you're done and
you'll have rock solid technique and
confidence on the keys and you'll just
be burning up the ivories and can you
see how this is much better to have a
plan to have a system that's been proven
over and over again to just take care of
your technique once and for all instead
of you know waffling around youtube and
saying you know today i'll just take
this random scale and this finger
exercise from this random video you kind
of feel like you're spinning your wheels
instead of just working smarter not
harder and having a plan and so this is
the plan for the technique portion of
your learning and so if you're
interested in learning that click this
video for the top four exercises for
piano beginners or if you're more just
interested in learning your favorite
songs from the radio in two minutes or
less click this video that will teach
you the step-by-step system to learn
that happy practicing and i'll see you
in the next one